# 佛山·顺德
Shunde, Foshan
# 现在天刚是有点蒙蒙亮
It is dawn now
# 天气还是有点小冷
It is a little bit cold outside.
# 起这么早就是为了喝一碗粥
I woke up this early to eat a bowl of congee
# 这个粥到底有什么特别的呢
How is the congee so special?
# 它就是人称 粥中爱马仕的
It is known as the Hermes of Congee
# 顺德生滚粥
Shunde Congee
# 听名字 是不是觉得有点奇特呢
It sounds a little bit intriguing, isn't it?
# 去看看吧
Let's go and take a look
# 你好 坐吧
- Hi
- Have a seat
# 不用点单吗
Do I have to place an order?
# 不用写 你看吃什么粥就行
We don't write down the orders, you just have to take a look at the available options
# 哦哦，这里看吃什么粥就可以
Oh, just take a look...
# 内心话：老板 你确定是问我 要吃什么粥吗
(Uncle, are you sure that I should consider about which congee I'm having?)
# 不应该问：来 看你想吃什么肉
(I thought you would ask me to consider about which types of meat)
# 这一盆盆摆的鸡肉 牛肉 鱼肉 猪肉
(There are chicken, beef, fish meat, pork, etc)
# 应有尽有
(The choices are a lot)
# 到底应该吃哪一种呢
(Which congee should I try?)
# 点这个 知道吃什么了
Let's order this! (-knew which to choose)
# 大哥 我要一个猪杂肉丸的
Uncle, I want a bowl of congee with pork organs and meatballs
# 对 再要一个牛肉鱼片的
Yeah, one more with beef and fish fillets
# 对
Yep
# 多少钱
How much is it?
# 2碗一共43块钱
43 Yuan for 2 bowls of congee
# 哇 这么多的肉
Wow, that's a lot of meat
# 哇 碗好大啊
Wow, that's a big bowl
# 谢谢
Thank you
# 别动 别动 烫
Stay here, be careful, it's very hot
# 那里有小碗 自己去拿一下 消毒柜那里
There are small bowls over the sanitization cabinet (for tableware), you can take it yourself
# 可以 可以
Okay, yeah
# 这就是咱们要的两碗生滚粥
These are the two bowls of congee that we ordered.
# 这个呢 就是加了鱼片和牛肉 这个是猪杂和肉丸
- This is the one with beef and fish fillet
- This is the one with pork organs and meatballs
# 一共是43块钱
That's a total of 43 Yuan
# 我喝粥从来没有用过这么大的碗
I've never eat congee with such big bowls
# 大到什么程度呢 就是这个勺
How big is it?
# 我放进碗里 它时不时地会自己滑落到里面
The spoon might sink into it sometimes
# 被粥淹没
"Submerged" by the congee
# 这好像不是碗是用盆装的生滚粥
These feel like food basins rather than bowls
# 我告诉大家 我本来还想再加点油条
Let me tell you guys, I wanted to add some more Youtiao initially
# 再加点别的
Add something else
# 后来上来这一碗 直接什么都不要了
But when the congee is served, I don't wany add-on anymore
# 今天早上就干了这一碗粥就足够了
The portion is enough for this morning's breakfast
# 不过这一碗也不一定能够喝得了
But I might even not be able to finish this bowl of congee
# 生滚粥 你看 米快被熬化了
Look at this, the rice have been cooked until softened
# 米 几乎没有一粒是完整的
Not much of the rice keeps its shape
# 粥喝起来就是香糯 咸中带些甘甜
The congee is very flavourful and thick
# 肉是提前腌制过的 所以吃起来
The meat have been marinated before
# 不是索然无味的
so they are not flavourless
# （店）它这边的招牌是猪杂生滚粥
The signature dish here is congee with pork organs
# 但是一些人吃不惯怎么办
But what if someone is not used to eating pork organs?
# 这一碟的姜丝酱油 可供解腥
This plate of julienned ginger with soy sauce can be used to reduce the intense flavour of pork organs
# 本来以为20多块钱一碗粥 会很贵
Initially, I thought that 20 plus Yuan for a bowl of congee is kind of expensive
# 但是这个料真的很多
But there are a lot of food ingredients in the congee
# 多到你每舀一勺 都会感觉这个肉 这个料沉甸甸的
You can feel the heaviness of the meat and the other ingredients every time you take a spoon of congee
# 多到吃不完
You might not even be able to finish it
# 这几天吃饭都是用的这种大圆桌
Most restaurants that we visit in these few days use this kind of big and round table
# 就是谁到谁先坐
You can sit whichever table if you are early
# 来晚的呢
If you are late during mealtime
# 可以随眼缘拼桌
You can sit with other people
# 咱们是来的比较早
We are relatively early
# 一些老人家早早来吃早饭
Some elderlies are having their breakfast very early in the morning
# 他们在吃生滚粥的时候
When they are having congee,
# 还会用白酒来配
they would pair it with Baijiu liquor
# 这个店是一对兄妹开的
This restaurant is run by a brother and a sister
# 做的是街坊邻居的生意
Most of the customers are the ones staying nearby
# 很多老人就直接把自己的酒瓶放在这边
Many elderlies keep their bottles of liquor at the restaurant
# 早上起来呢 就是喝粥配白酒
And they'll have congee with Baijiu liquor every morning
# 今天是这几天在顺德最冷的一天了
As I'm staying in Shunde for a few days, today's weather is the coldest
# 喝碗粥暖和暖和
Let's have some congee to warm myself up
# 你看 大早上起来我是这样
Look at my clothing in the morning
# 等到中午我就是另外一个面貌了
It would be totally different when it's noon
# 知道为什么这么冷吗 因为有风
Do you know why is it so cold today? -Because of the windy weather
# 如果说 没有风的话 应该会暖和很多
It would be much warmer if it's less windy today
# 蝎子炖品
Double boiled soup woth scorpions
# 一直以来 我们吃的东西都是平淡无奇的
In the past, we have been eating food that are really common
# 像猪肉牛肉羊肉这样的荤菜
Such as pork, beef and lamb
# 还有面 粉这样的主食
And also carbs like noodles and vermicelli
# 继去年来广州吃到蛇
After we tried eating snake meat in Guangzhou last year,
# 这次我们来顺德
We are in Shunde this time
# 来挑战一个不一样的美食品种 吃蝎子
to challenge a new type of delicacy, scorpions
# 听起来感觉有点恶毒的蝎子
Scorpions are often described as a malicious creature
# 把它炖着吃
If we double boil it as soup,
# 是不是还比较有意思呢
does it sound more interesting?
# 来 走吧
Okay, let's go!
# 你好 开始营业了吗
Hi, is the restaurant open yet?
# 可以了 哦
Yeah
# 进来坐吧 开门了 今天提前了5分钟开门
Have a seat, the restaurant is open 5 minutes earlier today
# 因为是周六周日的原因吗
Is it because today is weekend?
# 很少提前开门 一直都是标准时间开门
Most of the time we'll follow the official operating hours
# 今天心情特别好 知道你们来了
We are delightful to know that you are visiting today
# 所以 提前开门了
Thus, the restaurant is open slightly earlier
# 坐吧 随便做吧
Have a seat please
# 可以
Yeah
# 平常排队排很长时间都排不到你
Normally the queue is so long that I don't have the chance to try the food
# 平常排队都需要排队到12点
The crowd queue up from 12pm to 2pm everyday
# 排队排到怀疑人生
- That's really overwhelming
# 老板这边卖的最多的是什么呀
What's the bestseller here?
# 党参乌鸡蝎子汤 30多年来最受欢迎的
It's the black-bone chicken and scorpion soup with Dangshen
# 每天70%的客人都喝这个汤
Around 70% of the customers order this everyday
# 小心 这个碗很烫的 刚刚消完毒
Be careful, the bowl is very hot since it's just been sanitized
# 谢谢
Thank you
# 你稍等 坐在那里点就可以了
Wait a moment, you can order your food at your seat
# 我可以听到你说话
We can hear you
# 好的 我要一个党参乌鸡炖蝎子
Alright, I want the black-bone chicken and scorpion soup with Dangshen
# 然后 还有一个松茸炖乌鸡
Yeah, and the black-bone chicken with Matsutake mushroom soup
# 再加一个煎蛋 一份米饭
Yeah, and also a fried egg and a bowl of rice
# 煎蛋要几分熟 八分熟还是全熟
Do you want an egg over-medium or an egg over-hard
# 全熟！
An egg over-hard
# 一个白米饭
And a bowl of rice
# 一个蝎子汤　一个松茸乌鸡
Scorpion soup, and the Matsutake chicken soup
# 可以
Okay
# 你吃白米饭 要不要试试我们的榨菜
Since you're having white rice, do you want to try our "Zha Cai" (Chinese pickled mustard plant stem)
# 5块钱一份 可以
- Yeah
- 5 Yuan for one portion
# 是我们自己做的 跟外面的不一样
It's not the store bought one,. we make it ourselves
# 可以　五块钱一份
- Okay
- 5 Yuan each
# 好的
Yeah
# 因为我估计你没试过 当配菜可以试一下
Because I think that you've ever tried it before, you can eat it as a condiment
# 你可以在座位上点餐
You can order your food at your seat
# 老板直接在他的台子上
He'll take your order at the counter
# 专属舞台
The one and only "stage"
# 来记大家点了什么
for him to take your order
# 这边最贵的是1150元一份
The most expensive food is around 1150 Yuan here
# 但是需要预定
But it requires you to make reservation in advance
# 感觉吃不到 也吃不起
I think we couldn't have it today, and we aren't that rich
# 上菜了 好 谢谢
Okay, thanks
# 这个料汁是什么呀
What dipping is this
# 酱油
Soysauce
# 你觉得肉淡的话就蘸一下吃
You can dip your meat in the soup with this
# 蘸里面的肉吃的
If you think the meat is tasteless then you can dip it
# 闻着还是有中药材的味道的
You can smell the herbal in the soup
# 炖蝎子 听起来感觉很恶毒
Cooked scorpions, it sounds so malicious,
# 让人感觉很害怕
making people to be afraid
# 但是这个汤还是很清澈的
But the soup itself is quite clear
# 没有任何的浑浊物（让人难受）
It is not turbid
# 这一碗汤大概有五六只蝎子
You can see that there are around 5 to 6 scorpions
# 还有大块的乌鸡肉
and big chunks of black-bone chicken meat
# 先尝一口这个蝎子汤吧
Let's taste test the scorpion soup first
# 这个汤很清甜 还融入了乌鸡的香味
The soup is very tasty, rich in flavours of the black-bone chicken
# 老板 这个蝎子应该可以吃吧
Uncle, we can eat the scorpions right, can't we?
# 蘸一下酱油吃
You can dip it with the soysauce
# 咀嚼一下　能吞的就吞
Chew it, swallow the soft part
# 不能吞的当作骨头一样吐掉
Spit out the parts that are like bones
# 130
Yeah, I get it
# 这个蝎子能吃到的部分
Actually, the part of the scorpion that is edible
# 其实只有腹部这一部分
is the abdomen
# 其他的部位都吃不到肉
There isn't any meat at the other parts
# 这个肉感觉像鱼脑一样
The meat is similar to fish brain
# 一下子就吸溜进去了
Custardy and you can suck it
# 剩下的都是硬壳 要当骨头一样吐掉
The rest is its shell, you have to spit it out as if they are bones
# 其实 你看在广东 不仅有靓仔
Well, there isn't only Liangzai (nice-looking guys) in Guangdong
# 还有靓汤
there is also Liangtang (Awesome soup)
# 蝎子是作为一种食材
Over here, scorpions
# 直接炖汤吃
are considered as a type of food ingredient used in soups
# 在我小时候还见过
To be honest, I've seen that someone used scorpions to infuse liquor
# 用蝎子来泡酒的
when I was a little one
# 但是炖汤还是第一尝试吃
But it's my first time to try scorpions cooked in soup
# 请订阅频道
(Subscribe please)